I’m a music teacher & professional musician
who has made more than 500 keyboard & digital
piano reviews & comparisons on my channel and
I’m going to help you pick a keyboard, digital
piano or MIDI controller that best suits your
budget and the type of music you want to create.
Before I begin, here’s a quick tip. If you
are an absolute beginner, don’t spend too much
on your very first keyboard. You don’t need an
expensive keyboard to learn the basics. However,
if you can stretch your budget to buy a mid-tier
piano keyboard, you will find that they sound
much better, have better key action, are more
solidly built and have a higher resale value.
If you are mostly interested in learning and
playing piano pieces, get a digital piano on my
list that has 88 weighted keys. If you are more
into contemporary pop, rock, jazz & world music
or playing with a band, a synth action keyboard
is lightweight, cheaper and better for playing
non-piano sounds. A MIDI controller keyboard
does not come with any onboard sounds. Instead,
you use a MIDI keyboard to control virtual
instruments and music production software that
is installed on your computer, iPad or smartphone.
This video is not sponsored and I paid for these
keyboards. The prices I mention are accurate
as at the time of this video and in order not
to make this video 2 hours long, my in-depth
reviews, sound demonstration and best prices
for the keyboards and digital pianos in this list
are in the video description and comment section.
$100+
The beginner
keyboard with the biggest bang for your buck
is the $199 Yamaha’s PSR-E383. It comes with
61 touch sensitive synth action keys, 650 sounds
- which can be layered and split, more than 60
DSP effects and 260 rhythm accompaniments using
Yamaha’s time tested AWM sampling technology.
There are music lessons built into the keyboard
and you can use the onboard speakers or plug in a
pair of headphones. To record your performances,
there’s a 2 track song recorder and it can be
powered with an electrical outlet or using
6 “AA” batteries. The USB port supports both
MIDI & digital audio for use with music learning
apps and music production software. For $100 more,
there’s the 76-keys version PSR-EW320
- great for playing piano pieces or the
key-lights version EZ310 - which lights up
the keys to show you which notes to press.
If producing contemporary digital music
using virtual instruments and multi-track
recording software is more your cup of tea,
you won’t go wrong with the $100+ Impact GX61
MIDI controller keyboard from Nektar. It
has 61 touch sensitive synth action keys,
DAW transport controls, advanced MIDI integration
right out of the box for 10 of the most popular
music production software including the
bundled 8-track sequencer from Bitwig.
My full review, sound demo and best
prices for these $100+ keyboards
can be found in the description & comment section.
$200+
At $219, the Casio CT-S1 is a fantastic
61 keys keyboard for those who want one of the
best key actions and studio quality sounds at an
affordable price in an ultra-portable form factor
without all the bells & whistles. You get 61 of
the most usable studio quality tones powered by
Casio’s latest AiX sound chip. These sounds can be
layered and there are more than a few dozen reverb
& DSP effects. A power adaptor or 6 “AA” batteries
power the onboard speakers and you can plug in a
pair of headphones. The micro-USB port supports
MIDI for music learning apps and with a Bluetooth
adaptor you get wireless MIDI and audio streaming.
For an additional $30 more than the CT-S1,
the Casio CT-S400 in a similar ultra-portable
design gets you 600 tones which can
be layered and split and 200 rhythm
accompaniments for you to jam along with. You
get a good variety of reverb and DSP effects,
a 6 track song recorder and 32 user memory
to store your settings. The keyboard can be
powered with 6 “AA” batteries or with
a power adaptor and you can use the
onboard speakers or a pair of headphones.
A micro-USB MIDI port lets you connect to
music learning apps and a Bluetooth adaptor
gets you wireless MIDI and audio streaming.
For $299, there’s the Yamaha EZ310 and PSR-EW320.
The EZ310 is the key-lights version of the
PSR-E383 I talked about earlier on my list.
It is pretty much identical to the PSR-E383
except for the colour - white instead of black
and you get an additional 27 preset songs for
use with the key light and lesson features.
The Yamaha PSR-EW320 is also identical to
the PSR-E383 but with 76 instead of 61 keys
with everything else remaining the same. The
EW-320 is a good choice if you want the
extra 15 keys for your piano repertoire.
For digital music producers, the $269
Arturia Keylab Essential 61 MK3 is an
excellent choice. The 61 keys MIDI controller
comes with a great velocity sensitive hybrid
synth-piano key action, a rotary knob, 9
encoders, 9 faders, transport switches,
modulation and pitch bend wheels and
8 pressure sensitive pads for finger
drumming or triggering scenes. More than 2,000
sounds and virtual instruments from Arturia,
Native Instruments & UVI that cost up to
$1,000 are bundled with the controller
keyboard together with the industry leading
music production software Ableton Live Lite.
My in-depth review, sound demo
and best prices for these $200+
keyboards can be found in the
description & comment section.
$300+
For $349, Roland’s latest GO:Keys 3 keyboard is
unbeatable. Packed with more than 1,154 instrument
sounds - powered by Roland’s flagship Zen-Core
sound engine - which can be layered and split
across the keyboard, 203 performance ready rhythm
accompaniments, a user definable chord sequencer,
more than 100 effects, 256 user programmable
settings, onboard speakers and user expandable
sound & rhythms packs using Roland SoundCloud,
you will not find a more value for money
& competent 61-key keyboard at this price.
With both USB & Bluetooth, you get both wired &
wireless MIDI & audio streaming for use with music
learning apps & music production software. The
onboard song recorder records both MIDI & digital
audio which is great for sharing online and
this keyboard can be powered with batteries or
a power adaptor. The GO:Keys 3 is available
in 3 beautiful colours to fit your style.
Also at $349 is the Korg Liano, the best
sounding ultra lightweight 88-key digital
piano at this price. With 8 studio quality
Italian & German piano & electric piano
samples and loads of bundled virtual
instruments, this is a keyboard built
specifically for piano players. You get
reverb & chorus effects, onboard speakers,
a headphones jack, a sustain pedal input and
a USB port that handles both MIDI & digital
audio - great for music learning apps and music
production software. The keyboard can be powered
with 6 “AA” batteries or a power adaptor
and it’s available in 6 striking colours.
If you need an affordable 88-weighted keys
digital piano and do not need portability,
the Donner DEP-20 at just $350 is a great
bargain. With 238 instrument sounds which can
be layered and split across the keyboard, 200
rhythm accompaniments, onboard song recorder,
powerful speakers, a headphones jack and
USB MIDI for connecting to music apps,
the Donner DEP-20 gives tremendous
value for an absolute beginner.
If you pay $29 more, get the Alesis Recital
Pro. At $379, you get 88 touch sensitive
weighted piano style keys and 12 piano,
electric piano and organ sounds which can
be layered or split across the keyboard. A
simple song recorder, sustain pedal jack,
reverb & chorus effects, headphones jack and
USB MIDI for use with music learning apps
and music production software is included.
The onboard speakers can be powered with a
power adaptor or with 6 “D” size batteries.
You may find cheaper China brand 88 weighted
keys digital pianos but do yourself a favour
and don’t be penny wise and pound foolish.
For the digital music producer who is more focused
on piano repertoire, the $399 Arturia Keylab
Essential 88 MK3 is what you’re looking for. It
is identical to the $269 Keylab Essential 61 MK3
I talked about earlier, but with more keys and is
an absolute bargain for those who require 88-keys.
Check the description & comment
section for my in-depth review,
sound demo and best prices
for these $300+ keyboards.
$400+
2 of the best keyboards in the $400+
category are the $499 Roland GO:Keys 5 & $489
Yamaha PSR-EW425. The Yamaha has 76 keys whereas
the Roland has 61 keys but the Roland has 1,154
sounds versus the 820 sounds on the Yamaha. The
Yamaha has more accompaniment styles - 290 versus
the 203 rhythms on the Roland but the GO:Keys 5
gives you 4 variations for each style and it’s
really easy to expand the sounds and rhythm
accompaniments on the Roland using CloudConnect.
The Yamaha PSR-EW425 has more powerful onboard
speakers and has 2 live control knobs which the
Roland does not have. While both can record songs
on MIDI and digital audio, only the Roland has
the option for Bluetooth wireless connectivity.
The Alesis Recital Grand, also sold as
the Alesis Prestige in some markets,
is the only 88 graded hammer action digital pianos
in the $400+ price category I can recommend. You
get 16 high quality multi-sampled piano
and electric piano sounds which can be
layered and split across the keyboard,
a powerful 50 watt array speaker system,
dual headphone jacks, triple pedal support and a
USB MIDI port for use with music learning apps.
You can find my demonstration of the
sounds and my in-depth review of these
$400+ keyboards and digital pianos
in the description & comment section.
$500+
$599 seems to be the sweet
spot for a solid beginner 88 graded hammer action
digital piano. You won’t go wrong with either the
Roland FP-10, Yamaha P-145 or Casio PX-S1100.
The Roland FP-10 has 36 instrument sounds,
the most number in this category and the
Yamaha has the least at just 10 sounds,
but the Casio has the highest polyphony
at 192 notes. The Casio PX-S1100 is also
the most compact, lightweight and can be battery
operated whereas the other 2 can only be powered
off an electrical outlet. I prefer the key action
of the Roland FP-10 but the Casio has a lighter
action which beginners may benefit from. They all
have headphones jack and onboard speakers but the
amplification on the Casio is the most powerful
of the 3. Both the Roland FP-10 and Casio PX-S1100
have both USB MIDI and wireless Bluetooth
functionality to connect to music learning
apps and audio streaming while the Yamaha
P-145 has just a USB MIDI port. Nonetheless,
you will not go wrong with any of these 3 if you
are looking for your 1st beginner digital piano.
My in-depth review, sound demo and best prices
are in the description and comment section.
$600+
At $699,
the Roland FP-30X and Yamaha P-255 are great
choices for serious piano students who are on a
tight budget. You get really good key action
at these prices from both manufacturers and
there is a perceptible jump in sound quality,
build quality and note polyphony which are
important. The Yamaha P-255 has 24 high quality
tones whereas Roland packed more than 321 tones
in the FP-30X. You get dual headphone jacks,
triple pedal support, a song recorder, and stereo
aux audio outputs for connecting to more powerful
speakers or mixing decks for performances. While
both keyboards have USB MIDI for use with music
learning apps and music production software,
the Roland FP-30X supports wireless Bluetooth.
Do note that the speakers on the Yamaha P-255
are significantly more powerful than those found
on the FP-30X if that’s important to you. These 2
digital pianos are entry-level pro keyboards that
are often found in clubs, pubs and restaurants.
$800+
The $800+ mark is where
you will find my personal favourites - the hybrid
arranger digital pianos. The $849 Yamaha DGX-670
and the $899 Roland FP-E50 hybrid piano arrangers
are the best of both worlds. They have 88 graded
hammer action keys and have rhythm accompaniments
and music production capabilities. The Roland has
more than 1,000 sounds whereas the Yamaha has
600 voices but the Yamaha makes up for it by
having 263 rhythm accompaniment styles whereas
the Roland has just 177 styles. However, you can
expand the sounds and rhythm accompaniments on the
Roland FP-E50 using expansion packs available on
Roland’s CloudConnect whereas the DGX-670 has
more limited expansion options. The Yamaha has
4 variations for each rhythm accompaniment as
well as more granular rhythm track controls. A
rhythm style creator is also available on the
DGX-670 whereas the Roland does not have this
feature but has a chord sequencer instead.
Both hybrid arranger pianos have a mic input
and vocal effects if you want to sing and play.
However, I do wish the Roland has a colour high
definition LCD screen like the Yamaha but it only
has a monochrome screen. The Roland FP-E50 does
make up for it by having speakers that are twice
as powerful as the Yamaha DGX-670. You get every
imaginable connectivity option including wireless
Bluetooth but the Yamaha has a powerful 16 track
sequencer whereas the song recorder on the
Roland is a basic one. The bottom line is this,
if you want loads of sounds and expansion, get
the Roland FP-E50. If rhythm accompaniments and
music arranging is more important to you,
the Yamaha DGX-670 is the better choice.
$1,000
Here are my recommendations
in the $1,000 category. For digital pianos, the
$949 Kawai ES-120 and $999 Roland RD-08 are my
favourites. They feature great sound quality,
fantastic graded hammer action keys and solid
build quality. If you want a pro-level arranger
keyboard with rhythm accompaniments and more than
1,200 sounds, the $1,099 Yamaha PSR-SX600 is the
one you want to get. For gigs and performances,
the lightweight 61-key Yamaha CK61 stage
keyboard and the Roland Juno DS88 hammer
action stage synthesiser with thousands of sounds
and every imaginable feature a working keyboardist
needs gets my recommendation. The CK61 and Juno
DS88 can be powered with batteries or a power
adapter and these keyboards also work really
well as an advanced MIDI keyboard controller.
$1,000 Home Digital Pianos
For the more traditional console
home digital pianos that costs about $1,000,
the ones that impresses me the most when it
comes to sound quality and key action are the
made in Japan Korg LP-380U, the Yamaha YDP-S35,
the Casio PX-870 and if you can stretch your
budget a little more, the Roland F701 when
it comes to bang for buck. Home console pianos
usually cost more due to the cabinet work, the
significantly larger speakers and amplification
system, a bench and a triple pedal system.
You can find everything I recommend including
the music learning apps my students use in the
description and comment section. I hope you
found this video useful. My name is Jeremy
See and check out my in-depth video reviews
and sound demo if you need more information.